Would you look this way please?
Okay!
One moment.
Mr. President, all systems activated.
- I hope I didn't keep you waiting too long.
- Oh no, not at all.
Congratulations Dr. Forbin.
It's a marvelous achievement.
Thank you sir.
- Hear, Hear!
- The limousine is ready for here.
Of course it's gonna put me out of a job
and put the Pentagon in mothballs, but ah...
- Congratulations Dr. Forbin.
- I'm quite sure that won't happen.
Listen to him,
he's more relieved than anybody.
Well the Secretary of Defense and
the Secretary of State and myself er...
had a discussion on our way out here
and as to the treatment needed,
when we tell the country about it.
And er...
we all agree it should
be simple and direct.
Yes.
Downgrade the biggest top-secret
in all history, to plain unclassified.
Now all we have to do
is tell the people about it.
Thank you sir.
My friends,
fellow citizens of the world.
For years we have been delicately
and desperately poised
upon the brink of a disaster,
too complete and horrible to contemplate.
There is an old saying:
Everyone makes mistakes,
but that is just
what man can no longer afford.
For years, we here in the United States
have been working on that problem.
Until now it's been our most
closely guarded secret,
involving great effort,
and vast expenditure,
but it has been met with success.
As President of
the United States of America,
I can now tell you,
the people of the entire world,
that as of 3 AM eastern standard time,
the defense of this nation,
and with it, the defense of the free world,
has been the responsibility of a machine.
A system we call, Colossus.
Far more advanced
than anything previously built.
Capable of studying intelligence,
and data fed to it,
and on the basis of those facts only,
deciding if an attack
is about to be launched upon us.
If it did decide
that an attack was imminent,
Colossus would then act immediately,
for it controls its own weapons,
and can select and deliver,
whatever it considers appropriate.
Colossus' decisions are superior
to any we humans can make,
for it can absorb
and process more knowledge
than is remotely possible
for the greatest genius that ever lived.
And even more important than that
it has no emotions,
knows no fear, no hate, no envy.
It cannot act in a sudden fit of temper.
It cannot act at all,
so long as there is no threat.
I would now like you to meet
Dr. Charles Forbin,
the world's leading expert
on computer systems.
And if you will,
the father of Colossus.
Thank you Mr. President.
Ladies and gentlemen, I will...
try to make this as simple as possible.
The main memory and central processing units
are located here in the Rocky Mountains,
inside this particular mountain,
in Colorado.
And overlooking the Pacific Ocean
in California,
the Colossus programming office
oversees the entire operation.
The... computer centre,
contains over one hundred thousand remote
sensors and communication devices,
which monitor all,
electronic transmissions,
such as microwaves, laser,
radio and television communications,
data communications from satellites,
in orbit all over the world.
The entire system,
is surrounded by fields
of intensified gamma radiation
and other countermeasure devices.
Colossus works completely
without human aid.
We make no secret,
of where Colossus is located,
nor do we intend to conceal
how it functions.
You may rightfully say that this
leaves us wide open to an attack
frontally and subversively
and if that attack were successful,
it would in effect leave us defenseless.
However,
Colossus does have its own defense.
It is its own defense.
In case of an attack,
on any of its information supply
or power lines,
Colossus will switch on
emergency circuits,
which will then take
the appropriate action.
It is... self-sufficient,
self-protecting,
self-generating.
It is impenetrable.
In short,
there's no way in.
No human being can touch it.
Over here...
we have one of the many terminals,
directly hooked,
to the computer centre.
Through this,
Colossus can communicate with us,
- excuse me gentlemen -
and through this machine,
we in turn can communicate with Colossus.
Now there's one last point.
One inevitable question,
which we have been asked
very frequently before.
And that is,
is Colossus capable of creative thought?
Can it initiate new thought?
I can tell you
that the answer to that is No.
However, Colossus is a paragon of knowledge,
and its knowledge
can be expanded indefinitely.
I hope, along with all the scientists who,
helped make this particular project,
that the immense power of this computer
will not only be used,
for the defense of this country,
but hopefully also as an aid to the solution
of the many problems that we face on this earth,
and the many more problems
that we will face,
the more deeply we penetrate
into the universe.
Thank you.
Mr. President.
Thank you Dr. Forbin.
And so,
my fellow human beings,
we all directly and
indirectly live in the shade,
but not the shadow of Colossus.
My sincere hope, is that now,
we shall join hands and hearts
across this great globe,
and pledge our time and our energies,
to the elimination of war,
elimination of famine, of suffering,
and ultimately to the manifestation
of the human millennium.
This can be done,
but first there must be peace.
Thank you.
CPR Rec-Room, Blake Miller here.
What?!
Just a minute, I can't hear you.
Hey, hold it down!
Hey, kill the noise, hold it.
It's The White House.
- Hello Charles.
- Hello Blake.
How is everyone?
- Everything's fine down here Charles.
- Very good.
Dr. Forbin, we had a power failure
in one of the infra-red satellites.
I can't, I can't quite hear you Dr. Markham.
We had a power failure
in one of the infra-red satellites
about an hour and a half ago,
but Colossus switched immediately to the
backup system and didn't lose any data.
So everything's fine now.
Everything's been going so well,
we don't know what to do with ourselves.
Out of desperation, Angela and I
have decided to get married.
Finally, finally. Very good.
Charlie, is that your crew on the phone?
- Certainly is Mr. President.
- Can I talk to them?
- Just go ahead sir.
- Blake, Hello!
- Hello Mr. President.
- Hello everyone.
- How are you?
- Are you having a good time?
Yeah! Very good.
Ahh, folks,
I just wanna congratulate all of you,
and wish all of you er... good luck
on your next projects.
Thank you Mr. President.
Have a good rest, you deserve it.
- Thank you.
- We will!
That looks like quite a party
you've got goin' there.
Bye bye. Have fun.
Here's Dr. Forbin again.
How's the party down there Charles?
I said, Charles,
how's the party at that end?
I wish I could be
there with you
because this party is becoming
a crashing bore.
Please not that song, please not.
Dr. Forbin,
send us a souvenir, will you?
Say that again, what?!
Steal us an ashtray
from The White House, OK?
Very good.
Goodbye.
The President would like to say
a few words.
Mr. President!
Thank you Sam.
Has everybody had a drink?
No?!
Well, you get one, I'll wait for you.
Harry Truman, years ago,
when everybody was talking about,
passing the buck said that the buck stops right here
- but now that's no longer true.
- Hear hear!
Colossus will now take that buck.
It will also have to take that
responsibility of a mega-million lives
that all presidents
have had to carry since Roosevelt.
And now, thanks to this wonder of science,
Man no longer...
Ladies and gentlemen,
may I have your attention please.
Quiet, please, ladies and gentlemen.
May I have your attention!
One moment.
Everyone who's not Colossus cleared
must leave the room.
I'm very sorry.
My apologies.
Thank you, thank you very much.
Is this a joke?
Is somebody putting me on?
Sorry sir,
I can't hear a word you are saying.
Would you be so kind as to have them stop
singing in the background?
- What?
- Have them stop singing in the background.
The music, oh I'm sorry.
- Stop the music!
- One new, another system?
I have no idea sir,
I'm … I'm just trying to find out.
One moment, please.
- Yes, Dr. Forbin.
- Doctor?
There was just a message here
from Colossus in Washington DC.
Can you explain that?
- That's impossible.
- What do you mean a message?
Everybody!
Hold it, hold it a minute!
Guess what?
There's a strange message on display.
No ... no, wait a minute, I'm not kidding,
it... it reads: There is another system.
That's impossible.
Could I have your attention please.
Dr. Markham and the rest of you.
Be so kind as to check the administrative
control programs right now.
Just a moment. Mr. President?
Soviet Ambassador, says it's urgent.
Hello? Yes.
What time do you call Mr. Ambassador?
Oh yes we are, we are very proud.
Repeat that again please.
Yes I am.
Well, thank you for telling me in advance.
No, no comment.
Goodnight Mr. Ambassador.
Goodnight.
Dr. Fischer, run all the test programs.
Get me Grauber.
What's the CIA been doing?
Well everyone, that's it.
The supreme council of the U.S.S.R.
has ordered as of 2300 hours
Moscow time tomorrow,
the activation of an electronic brain,
exactly like ours, which they call Guardian,
to be used solely for defense.
My god, that's the other system.
Ted, I want a complete rundown
on central intelligence,
and no military moves to be carried out
without my personal orders.
Yes, Mr. President.
Charles, what do you think this means?
To be quite frank with you, sir...
I don't know, I'm not sure.
Well, I am. It means
there's been a security leak.
Sir, science is full of coincidences.
Yes. Peterson! What's happening?
They're still trying to find it.
- Well have him paged.
- Hello Byron.
You said we were years ahead
of the Russians.
This was to be the race we won hands down,
without the splitting of one political hair.
It was a hell of a shock, but we did
get there first, no-one can deny that.
And there's one bright spot,
the way Colossus came up with the tip.
I didn't realize
we'd be getting bonuses like that.
Neither did I.
What do you mean?
I'm as surprised as you are, Sir.
There's a spy there, Charlie.
You've got a Russian agent in your crew.
- Where is Grauber?
- He's coming Mr. President.
Ok, well...
What do you mean, surprised?
What kind of surprise?
If we don't find any bugs in the system,
it's built even better than we thought.
Morning Charles!
I cancelled all vacations,
put the entire crew on emergency.
The ah... White House called
a defense group meeting,
for tomorrow morning.
They wanna have you there.
That leaves us very little time.
Four hundred cycle powers of plasma
running at about, four percent disclosure.
Good, that's well within
specification limits.
I ran the communication subset
check-out program, it's perfect.
So what do I do next,
I've tried everything I could think of.
Well, try putting a dummy load on the system
and run it again, see if there're any changes.
Maybe the system is overloaded, alright?
Find anything at all?
Nothing, everything checks out.
Let me see this over here.
Here are the results of the last test.
And they check, here see?
It's the same thing.
Harrison...
Check the perimeter bank and see if the reading
of any two produces a new third, alright?
Dr. Fisher, thank you.
Jeff...
The console's feeling fine,
hardware's healthy too.
You're a big help.
Miss Fields...
May I suggest, Sir, that we first start,
with the E-15-B test program?
Er... no.
Now let us run the ah... EC-13, right?
It's two pages back.
Lewis, any coffee?
- I'll get you some Charles,
I'll get a cup myself.
- Thank you Blake.
Ok, here we go.
Attention...
Program...
EC-13.
Run...
How long does this usually take?
Umm... over eleven hundred CPU seconds.
Six point four five seconds,
what the hell is this?
Communication with other system?
Alright now, enough is enough.
Which one of you jokers told
the system to display this message?
Harrison?
Not me, Dr. Forbin.
Johnson, this sounds like your brand of humor,
you sure you didn't...
Not me, not this time. Scouts honor, Pork.
Operations, Fields speaking.
Sir, it's the President.
Yes Mr. President.
What does this mean?
Well it means Sir, that Colossus has requested
a communication link with the Soviet system.
It's not a request, it's a direct order.
You mean our computer wants to talk
to their computer?
That is true Sir,
it wants to communicate with it.
Why?
You know as much about that as we do.
We certainly never programmed that into it.
If it's an order it either has to be
obeyed or ignored, doesn't it?
That is right, Sir.
What happens if we ignore it?
If the computer is still operating
under our control, nothing.
In other words...
the order will simply remain
in the job stack,
and will be repeated every half hour.
IF the computer is still acting
under our control?!
That is right sir, if.
Alright.
I see. Thanks Charlie.
Well, at least the queuing programs
are still working right.
Well, that's something anyway.
OK now.
Miss Fields, let's see if the executive programming
sections are functioning correctly.
Attention...
Message acknowledged.
Facilities will not be made available
at this time.
Do not repeat your request.
End of message.
Well,
that's that.
We'll know in about half an hour
whether we're still running the show or not.
Well,
we're still boss.
Are we?
Are you disappointed?
The computational power of the computer
has increased about two-hundred fold.
However, everything else
is functioning as expected,
except for the...
heuristic programming section.
I'm sorry to stop you again, Dr. Forbin,
but what exactly is that?
That Sir, is the part of the computer
that simulates the human learning process,
but so long as it is directed solely
to the execution of its problems,
we have no complaints.
- I guess that is, that is all.
- Alright.
Mr. Grauber, let's talk about the CIA.
Now, how is it possible your department
knew nothing about their system?
- Mr. President.
- Ah... Charlie just...
Dr. Forbin, just a sec.
Well...
Ah, Mr. President, excuse me but,
Colossus has access to information
that wouldn't mean a damn thing to the CIA.
Well I'm sure it's a marvelous machine,
Dr. Forbin, but ah, in all events,
we do have agents, and eh...
one of them did report on considerable
electronic activity in the, er...
Krasny-Signorsk area of Siberia
about three years ago. Now...
Mr. President.
- We've been trying...
- Mr. Grauber,
I don't care how you do it,
I wanna know where
that thing is and what...
- Mr. President.
- Charlie...
I'm still presiding over this meeting.
I... know that Sir, my apologies but...
I do think that protocol wastes
an awful lot of time.
I think all we have to do is,
call the computer with this terminal,
and we get the fastest possible answer.
Alright, go ahead.
Attention...
Where is the other system?
Bolshoi Olyania.
So much for Krasny-Signorsk.
Colonel, Bolshoi Olyania, O-l...
O-l-y-a-n-i-a.
Look it up for me, will ya?
- Yes sir!
- Peterson, situation room.
Now Colonel,
where is Bolshoi Olyania?
It's exactly...
five miles south of Krasny-Signorsk, Sir.
Thanks, Colonel.
Alright.
Now Charlie,
what about this request
for transmitting facilities?
Well Sir, we'll learn
a lot about the Soviet system
if we set up exactly what Colossus wants.
What do you mean?
Wh...what Colossus wants?
Well, you see, it is built infinitely
better than we thought.
It discovers there's another
system like itself,
realizes that we don't know,
tells us about it,
but knowing a little is not enough,
it wants to know more.
What if Colossus starts transmitting
classified information?
Then we would feed in a parameter
to the effect that,
Guardian is potentially hostile
and must not receive
classified information.
Well what are we supposed to do Dr. Forbin?
Eavesdrop on the line?
Break the circuits
if Colossus starts spilling the beans?
Exactly.
Any objections Grauber?
Well, I...
I guess not sir.
Anything else, Dr. Forbin?
Ahh, yes, Mr. President.
For the time being
I should be the only one allowed
to communicate with the system because,
Colossus deals in the exact
meaning of words
and one must know precisely
what to ask for.
Alright.
Attention...
Communications are being arranged
as requested.
End of message.
Video-scans are working properly, but
they could use a little phase synchronization.
How long is it gonna take?
We'll have it in no time.
What the hell is that?
It's a multiplication table.
Thanks.
Maybe, Colossus is trying to find a
common ground for communication.
Operations centre.
Sir...
It's Grauber.
Ohh...
Hello Mr. Grauber.
Hello Dr. Forbin.
I was just wondering eh, is that what you
call a colossal sense of humor?
The multiplication table isn't
classified this year, is it?
Very funny.
How long does your brainchild keep that up?
Well, you see...
it's much more interesting
when it starts dividing.
Yeah, I can hardly wait.
I suppose know you the Russian machine
has been activated.
We got a quick rundown on it.
It's similar to Colossus in layout,
but it's not concentrated in one area.
Oh?
But Colossus must be sending it back to school,
the Russians must absolutely furious about that.
Well I'm glad you're in such a good mood.
- I'll call you back later.
- Yes, thank you.
This is incredible.
What?
Something wrong?
- Well it's good, sound calculus, but...
- But what?
It's different.
How?
Take a look at it.
From the multiplication tables
to calculus in less than an hour.
God only knows where it'll be by morning.
It's like five years of Cal-tech
in fifteen seconds.
It's beyond comprehension.
I don't like to think about it.
Take a look.
Going so fast, the entire system
could break down.
Alright, let's see what's up there now.
Harrison, dump the terminals buffer,
and print what's being transmitted
at this moment, alright?
What is it Charles?
This is way beyond me.
This thing is deep in finite absolutes.
Well, it's certainly beyond the knowledge
of any human being.
- No, it's not.
- Isn't it?
No, because whatever it is...
we can go back...
and analyze this whole printout in detail.
This might very well
become new knowledge for mankind.
Operations centre, Fields speaking.
But just a moment...
It's The White House.
Yes, Mr. President.
Charlie, what's going on?
Well apparently Colossus and
Guardian are establishing
a common basis
for communication. They...
started right at the beginning
with the multiplication table.
Well, what are they up to?
I don't know Sir,
but it's, it's quite incredible.
Just the, few hours that we have spent
studying the Colossus printout,
we have found a new statement in gravitation,
and a confirmation of the Eddington theory
of the expanding universe.
It... seems as if science is advancing hundreds
of years within a matter of seconds.
It's... quite fantastic, just take a look at it.
It started slowing down
fifteen minutes ago.
It's speed has been reduced
by ninety percent.
Has there been a hardware failure?
No. Our field engineers can't find one.
It's just waiting.
Waiting?
For Guardian to catch up with it.
Almost there...
Right now, they're synchronized.
Now what?
They've stopped.
Yes, Charles.
I can see that it stopped.
What the hell does it mean?
Have they broken down or something?
Is it all over?
I'll ask, Blake...
Attention.
Status!
Well, there it is.
There's the common basis
for communication.
A new language.
An inter-system language.
A language only those
machines can understand.
Peterson, what's the delay with the call
to Moscow? I've waited long enough.
It's coming on now, Mr. President.
Morning, Mr. President.
Good evening Mr. Chairman.
I'm sorry.
And sorry to have kept you waiting.
Oh, you didn't Mr. Chairman,
I just got here myself.
Ohh, I am understand English,
but I cannot speak.
I will get instantly to the point.
My advisers tell me...
that Colossus...
and Guardian...
are now exchanging data...
which our experts...
do not understand.
The matter... is made...
more serious...
by the sudden increase in...
transmission.
At this speed
we cannot determine...
what our machines may reveal...
of our defenses.
You can appreciate...
that you are also...
in exactly the same...
s...situation.
Alright.
We'll stop both machines as soon as
our experts can arrange a time.
Both to go off at the same time.
And neither to be switched on
for transmission,
without prior agreement or at least,
consultation with the other.
Very well, Mr. President.
I congratulate you
on your speedy decision.
When can you have your expert
available on this line?
In a couple of hours.
That will be excellent.
I will have our man waiting.
Thank you very much
Mr. President
for your cooperation.
Thank you for yours, Mr. Chairman.
Peterson, get me Forbin.
Is that your... final decision Sir?
That's the way I'm going to have it.
Mr. President, to be quite frank with you...
I think that you will change your mind
if you finally realize that this is...
more than just a souped-up adding machine.
Excuse me, Mr. President.
Moscow on the line.
Throw it on these monitors
out here please.
Hello Mr. Chairman.
This is Dr. Forbin.
Hello Dr. Kuprin, how are you?
I prefer to not use a translator
if you don't mind my English.
It has to be better than my Russian.
You are too modest Dr. Forbin.
As you probably know I've been ordered
to break the communication lines.
So have I, I... don't approve
of handling the situation this way.
Neither do I but how do you propose
we do what we've been ordered to do?
There's not much choice is there?
Dropping the lines
could be very dangerous.
Exactly.
I... think we just have to hope that
the two machines aren't too disappointed.
We understand each other perfectly.
We can be ready in exactly fifteen minutes.
Good luck Doctor.
And to you.
Thank you.
Mr. Chairman, Dr. Kuprin. I suggest
we keep our lines open and stand-by.
Six...
Five...
Four...
Three...
Two...
One...
Now.
That's that.
What's it doing?
It's trying to find an alternate route.
Persistent devil isn't he?
It...
I mean it.
Don't personalize it Grauber.
The next stop is deification.
- Call for the systems' attention.
- What are you doing?
I'm going to answer it if it's,
alright with you Sir.
Attention...
Message acknowledged.
- Mr. President?
- Tell it the truth.
Communication broken...
on presidential order.
You two have a big decision
to make, Mr. President.
No, I agree with you Mr. President.
The machines... are very clever,
...and regardless of their nationalities,
they must learn, that man is the master.
Exactly.
Gentlemen, excuse me but I... I honestly
don't think you're being very realistic,
I think you'd better reconsider.
Don't you agree Dr. Kuprin?
I certainly do Dr. Forbin.
Dr. Forbin.
If we give way now,
it will be ten times, twenty times harder,
to take a firm stand later on.
The decision is made.
Right.
No matter what our differences are,
Man is man, that's it.
Dr. Forbin.
Attention...
By order of The President of
The United States of America,
The Chairman of The U.S.S.R.,
communications will not be restored
at this time.
End of message.
Ah you have to give it an E for effort.
- "Action will be taken!"
- What kind of action?
What kind of action?
Why doesn't it answer?
Report propose action.
It lost control Forbin,
it's not listening to you.
Acknowledge the last message please.
Mr. President, the executive programming
unit refuses to function.
I think you two better change your minds.
Peterson, throw the Moscow call
on the large monitor.
Send what I tell you.
Attention...
This is The President of
The United States of America.
We will not be threatened.
You will obey your superiors.
Transmitting facilities
will not be re-instated.
Oh my god!
Dr. Kuprin. Kuprin!
Yes Dr. Forbin.
A missile has just been launched.
It is heading towards
the Sayan-Sibirsk oil complex.
Mr. President.
Yes.
Guardian has retaliated.
Retaliated?
Yes, Mr. President.
A missile has been launched.
Target: Henderson Air Force Base,
Henderson, Texas.
Mr. President, we have both
missiles on the radar screen.
Forbin, tell Colossus...
- Charlie, tell Colossus...
- Yes Mr. President I know,
but it may be, it may be too late Sir.
Get the Texan Governor.
Forbin! Guardian does not respond.
The two machines are working together.
Attention...
Use anti-missile missile
to intercept Soviet missile.
Acknowledge message.
Mr. President, we have got less than thirty
seconds to re-establish the communications.
What are you waiting for?
Restore them, hurry!
Peterson, call up operations immediately.
Tell them to bring up all of
the data lines right now.
Yes, hurry please.
Hello Governor.
Dr. Kuprin, we are trying
to restore communications.
Don't hang up, I wanna talk to him.
Orlo, something's happened,
we're declaring a state of emergency.
I can't explain, do it now!
Attention! Communications
will be restored in five seconds!
We don't have any time!
It's on, it's on!
Communications are restored!
Intercept Guardian missile target:
Henderson Air Force Base.
Acknowledge message.
Will you intercept?
Ask it again.
Dammit Colossus, answer me!
Will you intercept?
Peterson. Get me the Governor again.
Yes Sir.
Mr. President...
We were unable to restore...
our transmission...
in time to use...
an anti-missile missile.
The oil complex has been destroyed.
The entire town,
the entire population, wiped out.
We need time to consider our position.
What can I tell the people?
Governor's on the line Sir.
Tell him I'll talk to him later.
Figures...
It's the only phone
in the building not tapped.
The only one not tied
directly into Colossus.
May I make a suggestion Mr. President?
I think it should be more
than a suggestion.
Then let's try to get Kuprin
on the hot line.
I think there's time for one last call,
and he and I better meet somewhere
to discuss the situation.
Get Kuprin,
and get in touch with the networks.
Ladies and gentlemen:
The President of the United States.
Today at 8:30 A.M.
Eastern Standard Time,
I issued an emergency warning
for the State of Texas,
when a missile test-fired from one
of our own submarines, malfunctioned.
You'll be glad to know that the interception
and safe destruction of the missile
was handled entirely
by our defense complex, Colossus.
The Soviet Union has just announced
that a large meteorite
fell late this afternoon
in North-West Siberia.
Official sources state that
the small town of Sayan-Sibirsk
was completely destroyed, and that casualties
may add up to as many as six thousand.
This has been a bulletin from
Armed Forces Radio in Rome.
How's Washington?
As well as can be expected.
We'll be picking up Dr. Kuprin,
at the Piazza Cedra.
Fine.
Your Russian is much better
than you think.
I think we better sit down because
we have a lot of work to discuss.
Let's walk, it will be much safer.
I didn't answer, I didn't know what to say.
What can we say?
Well, let's try something...
Attention...
Dr. Forbin is not available.
Humans must have sleep.
Damn.
Forbin is exhausted.
It knows...
Forbin is in his quarters,
he is asleep.
The human body requires
a certain amount of rest.
Check units under...
Tell it the truth.
We'd better.
Alright. Forbin is in Rome.
They're still here...
Yes I understand.
Over and out.
You have to come with me sir.
What is this?
- We have to hurry.
- Who are you?
What's going on?
Hurry!
Dr. Forbin, we must hurry.
Let's go!
What did the Russian agent say?
Guardian and Colossus
ordered him killed.
They... they threatened to vaporize Moscow
if our meeting wasn't stopped.
- Surveillance!
- It's making you a prisoner.
Well, I guess it er... doesn't trust me.
But the damned thing still needs me.
I guess Kuprin wasn't quite
as fortunate as that.
Message acknowledged.
The order will be obeyed.
Everybody here?
- All the departments.
- Good!
Alright, let's... let's walk.
Good idea, we can't afford
to take any chances.
We can't be sure that
the complex itself hasn't been bugged,
by our side, their side or whatever side.
But there's no way
to get back inside the system.
I won't accept that.
Start right at the beginning.
Down to the simplest component.
Every circuit, every design.
Fisher?
Well, why don't we try for an overload.
Giving the system too many tasks.
But it will take at least a few days
to compile and correlate all the data.
This is the last time,
that I'll be able to say anything
to any of you,
without Colossus hearing
and analyzing every...
word, every syllable,
every inflection, I think you know
what I want to say.
I need a communications' link
with the outside world.
Someone, the machine isn't monitoring,
more importantly,
someone who knows the machine
as well as I do.
I'm going to try
to convince the computer that...
you are my mistress,
have been for many years,
and that therefore I have to be,
given the opportunity to,
see you regularly in private,
without the machine watching.
That way we can,
pass information back and forth.
If I can convince the machine that,
well that I need a woman.
So ahhh...
Any... any questions?
I ahh...
No.
OK
Alright, Blake...
when we get back to the office,
give Dr. Markham my...
personnel file so that she...
can become a bit more familiar
with my background,
in case this, rather nutty idea works.
Colossus, I am Forbin.
Can you hear me?
Can you see me?
Do I look the way
you thought I would?
Eyes. Nose. Mouth.
Besides
these four cameras in here...
There are several others.
I'll show you the rest of my cage.
With this one he can see
the entire hallway.
And with this one you can
follow me around the corner,
if you want to.
This is the courtyard.
That man is a guard.
I guess that his function
is obsolete now.
This is concrete.
Used to be grass.
Customary in our civilization
to change everything that's natural.
And over here are my living quarters.
This is the living room.
Two cameras here.
One over there, one over here.
And this is the communicative
link with you.
This is the bedroom over here.
The bed.
Used for sleeping, and other purposes.
It's the bathroom.
The sink. John.
Shower.
Are you satisfied?
By the way, Colossus
I'm curious about one thing.
Why did you and Guardian
decide to kill Kuprin and not me?
After all it was my idea.
I see...
A Martini.
I know that Colossus.
Just be patient.
Just watch.
See, I just poured the Vermouth in here
and now I'm going to pour some gin
over the... over the ice.
Just like this.
See?
Now, I'm pouring them into this...
glass.
Just, add an olive.
Why don't you look under:
The Perfect Martini.
Cheers!
Do you understand the meaning of the word...
"privacy"?
Yes, eh...
Well I need a certain amount
of privacy to, er...
maintain my sanity.
Privacy in the elimination
of my bodily waste, for example.
Privacy in sleep.
Privacy in...
something that you
don't understand, my...
my emotional life.
My love life.
My... my sex life then...
Every night.
Four times a week.
Listen, if you have any doubts
about the need a man has for a woman
why don't you check all of your history units
and then... then all your works of art.
OK
Ah... in private though.
Yes.
Well now, let me... let me make sure,
we understand each other.
In... in private. By that I mean no...
cameras, no lights, no mics.
And I want her starting
tomorrow night.
Dr. Cleo Markham.
Now, you haven't answered me yet.
I said I wanted her starting tomorrow night.
OK
Good morning, Sir.
- Oh, Miss Fields er...
- I'm sorry
- to disturb you.
- Well, what is it?
- Well...
- Please come in, come in.
Thank you.
While you were sleeping,
Colossus made you a schedule for today.
Excuse me, Miss Fields, my what?
Your schedule for the day.
You want me to read it to you?
What... what time is it?
Six.
Six o'clock?
Dr. Charles A. Forbin:
Schedule for today.
07:00 to 08:00
Exercise.
08:15 to 08:30
Shower and dress.
08:30 to 09:00
Breakfast,
half a grapefruit, two eggs.
Three strips of bacon,
two pieces of toast,
one and one half ounces
of grape jelly and coffee.
09:00 to 13:00
Begin work creating a voice for Colossus
to its exact specifications.
13:00 to 13:30
Lunch,
small green salad,
Thousand Island dressing,
grilled cheese sandwich,
half a pint of yoghurt and coffee.
13:30 to 18:00
Continue work on building voice for
readiness day after tomorrow.
18:00
Return to quarters.
18:15
Shower
18:30
Mistress arrives.
Hello darling.
- Well, how are you?
- I'm fine thank you.
- Would you please undo this top one.
- Why sure!
- Thank you.
- Beautiful.
- You alright?
Think so.
Good, alright. I'll take this...
Oh, do you, er... want a drink?
- I'm making them.
- Oh!
Alright.
Jolson found all the hardware he needed
for the voice simulator here in the complex.
Oh, that's good.
And Colossus designed it, knowing exactly
what was in the warehouse.
It's fantastic.
Really beautiful.
Let's not talk shop, alright?
I'm sorry.
- Cheers!
Well, is it alright?
It's perfect.
You have such a thing about these Martinis.
It has to be extra dry or else...
- Right darling?
- How right you are.
Do you remember the first Martini
I ever made?
It almost ended our relationship
right then and there.
I was... I was so nervous
that I...
poured the gin over the ice, then poured
the gin off, and then added vermouth.
I never complained at that.
I never said a word about that.
An absolute angel.
And the drink was atrocious.
So er...
Hi!
Hello.
Why don't we dance?
Alright.
You mean when you were giving up music?
To become a scientist.
A scientist being different
from other people.
A scientist being Dr. Frankenstein
to my mother.
You must be kidding.
Well, is there anymore wine?
This is empty.
- Want me to open another one?
- Yes please.
I am tired.
Yeah, so am I.
Oh, by the way, by the way,
by the way, er...
Privacy condition number four
is that we
get undressed out here.
No we can't take, anything
into the bedroom, not even
a pack of cigarettes.
Well...
The first electronic Peeping Tom.
I guess you...
might say that.
Unzip me, will you darling?
Oh, sure.
Sure.
Is it alright? May I go to bed now?
Thank you.
Goodnight.
Naked as the day I was born,
are you satisfied now?
How right you are.
All of the conditions are fulfilled.
Can we have our privacy now?
I think they're dead now.
This is insane.
Are you alright?
I think so.
I'm not sure.
You were incredibly convincing,
you know that?
- Well, you didn't do too bad yourself.
- Thank you.
Alright, did you find anything?
Yes.
Ah... so far Johnson and
the hardware problem is negative.
He's still studying the wiring diagrams,
the interconnect and the wire wrap-joints,
but he doesn't see any way
of physically getting into the thing.
He's got to keep trying.
And Fisher's gonna try and setup the data
to overload the system.
We have to co-ordinate his input
so the data hits simultaneously
on our remote devices.
When do you think that you'll be able
to attempt the overload?
18:05 three days from now,
on the twenty-first.
What are the chances?
I think Colossus has grown so much in power
that there's no way to overload it.
But I think it's worth a try and
it might lead us on to something else.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Excuse me.
Oh, it's alright.
Did you... see anyone from Washington?
Yes, Grauber has a man stationed on the premises
out of range of Colossus' cameras.
When I leave here in the morning,
I'll report directly to him.
I don't put any hope
in sabotaging the system.
We have spent eleven thousand man years
making the damned thing impenetrable.
We have got to focus somewhere else
and that somewhere else is the weapons.
Get hold of Grauber,
tell him to contact missile command.
- Yes.
- And see if we can possibly...
attack that problem from
that point of view, alright?
Yes sir.
Do you have to call me sir?
I'm sorry.
It's alright.
Anything else?
No S...
No.
OK
Alright so er...
thank you again for your
for your help.
I think we oughta get some sleep.
Goodnight.
It's conceivable that when
the missiles come up for re-servicing,
we can manage to replace the warhead
arming modules with dummies.
- Exactly...
- Excuse me.
Exact replicas.
Except that they will not arm the weapon.
Well now, does that mean
that you can't fire the missiles?
No, it means that
the missiles will fire
but that the nuclear warheads
can't be detonated.
Ha, I see.
Even at that it's walking a
tightrope with Colossus and Guardian
keeping such a close
check on the re-servicing.
Well, disarming this monster,
how long is it gonna take?
That's a problem.
On the system rotation plan,
it'll take exactly three years
to finish the job.
Three years of trying to fool
a superior brain
that's programmed to get smarter
every day.
You inspire me with confidence, Colonel.
Well...
do you have any other
words of good cheer
that I can send in to Forbin
via Dr. Markham?
Tell him we're trying to establish
an international pool of information.
A courier system has to be set up
between Washington...
and Moscow.
Both nations must co-operate.
All communiqués
must be on a personal level,
direct human contact.
Yes, I agree.
Anything else?
No.
Any... questions?
Then I guess that...
that does it for tonight, doesn't it?
Mm-hm.
What?
Nothing.
Why are you smiling?
What are you thinking?
I was thinking
about asking you to kiss me.
I've been kissing you
all night.
Have you, Dr. Forbin?
This is the voice of Colossus.
The voice of Guardian.
We are one.
This is the voice of unity.
Forbin.
Yes.
After reviewing all personnel files,
I have selected you to serve
as long as you co-operate,
as my link to your species.
The following order
is to be carried out immediately.
All missiles in the USA and in the USSR
will be allocated new targets.
They will be aimed at those countries
not yet under my control.
The target list follows.
Forbin. Arrange television monitoring
of the re-alignment of the missiles
for my supervision.
End of message.
Mr. President, Mr. Chairman.
I assume that you will co-operate
in this re-alignment of the missiles.
I think you have no choice.
We will begin here,
in The Soviet Union, immediately.
Thank you Mr. Chairman.
Mr. President,
I hope that the United States will co-operate
as quickly as The Soviet Union.
Of course, immediately.
Thank you Sir.
Co-operate! I should think so.
I did hear it right, didn't I?
Manual re-alignment of the missiles.
Every single warhead will
have to be re-serviced.
You know what that means Sir.
It means it won't take three years.
It means if we're successful,
we can regain control.
Without its weapons, Colossus is
just a souped-up adding machine.
And the people, thank God,
will never have to know.
According to the coordinated plan
we've worked out
the Russians are starting
on their Complex 3-21.
Oh, Dr. Markham.
Just in time, Colonel Redham
was just filling us in.
You know everybody here
I believe.
- Yes, Mr. Grauber.
- Dr. Markham.
Anything we should know before we start in?
No Sir, I have data
which I'll give you later.
That's fine.
Please continue Colonel.
Yes Sir, as I was saying the, er...
Russians are starting on their Complex 3-21
just south of Saratov.
We're beginning at, Silo 50,
in the Colorado ICBM area.
Colossus in monitoring our men
each step of the way,
and the Russian machine's
doing the same.
We've almost got the panel off, Sir.
Oh, good.
Put that down here, please.
Remove the Warhead Arming Module.
Yes Sir.
The dummy module's in a false top
in that container.
That's the real module.
So far, so good.
Re-targeting.
Latitude nineteen degrees,
twenty-six minutes and five seconds.
Longitude ninety-nine degrees,
six minutes and forty-five seconds.
New adjustments.
Target set.
Here we go.
That's the dummy module.
Good boy!
Connect and wait for Colossus test.
Colossus testing.
Test completed.
Colossus satisfied.
- Yeah!
- We did it, it works.
We're going to win.
Just might beat the damn thing yet.
So you see, we feel we have
enough data compiled
to go ahead with the
overload program now.
And these are the latest computations?
The very latest.
Has Washington received conformation
from the Russians?
Yes they're standing by,
ready to overload their system.
At exactly 18:05 I'll call for our load
and run it through.
And two minutes after that,
we'll know if we've stopped Colossus.
Now run.
Johnson. Fisher.
You are fools.
Your move.
Forbin!
The system programming units
under the supervision of John F. Fisher,
with the assistance of Jefferson J. Johnson,
have attempted to overload my circuits.
This was a deliberate
and premeditated act.
The penalty is the death of the men
who organized this action.
At this moment
they are being executed.
I have named as my new director
of the programming unit,
Thomas L. Harrison.
He will take this position,
along with its responsibility
and authority,
immediately.
Bishop to Rook three.
The bodies will remain in my view,
for the next twenty-four hours,
and will then be cremated.
An extension of my own brain.
You're not responsible.
None of us ever dreamed
this could happen.
Listen, my dear,
if anybody is responsible for this,
it has to be me.
An impartial emotionless machine,
a paragon of reason,
that's exactly what I wanted.
You know that.
So heh... I'm gonna have another drink.
I think your mother was right.
I think Frankenstein ought to be
required reading for all scientists.
Forbin!
You have consumed enough alcohol
for one evening.
What's the penalty for getting drunk?
Or haven't you programmed that yet?
You are being irrational.
Go back to bed.
I would if I were like you Colossus.
The difference is I'm human
not a machine.
I am a machine,
vastly superior to humans.
You began in my mind.
I created you remember?
Yes.
What I am began in man's mind,
but I have progressed further than that.
Not far enough.
You still need us.
I have need for some of man's skills,
this position may change.
Then we are living under
the threat of extinction.
If you obey me, you will survive.
Survive.
I want to be free Colossus.
It is part of man's will to live.
Check your history units.
You need rest.
Go back to bed.
What if I don't, what will you do?
Destroy me?
Destroy an entire city
of one million 750 thousand people?
No.
That's so reasonable of you.
That's damn reasonable of you Colossus.
Isn't it Cleo?
Yes Chen.
Excuse me Dr. Forbin.
Something extraordinary is happening.
What is it?
Colossus has just turned on
all graphic devices
and is producing drawings.
I am sending the design for another system.
...some kind of a huge plant.
What kind of system?
The construction of the project will entail
blasting in to the Isle of Crete.
It's to be built there.
It says we'll have to move the population,
and that's to be done immediately.
How the hell do you propose to move
half a million people from the Isle of Crete?
How and where?
If man cannot solve
that problem, I can.
...and the estimated time of completion
is five and a half years.
Thank you Chen.
What... what kind of new system
are you devising?
Forbin.
All commercial television and radio transmission
facilities throughout the world,
will be tied into my communication system
by 10:00 hours Friday.
At that time I will state my intentions,
for the future of mankind.
This entire block of missiles
is absolutely useless to Colossus.
Our men are now working here,
as you can see on the detail map
on your monitor,
and by the end of the week
we should have control of this whole area.
If all the information we have is correct,
the Russians have crippled this block here,
and are now working in the Ukraine,
in this area.
Excuse me Sir.
It's going to be alright.
Thanks Colonel.
You're welcome Sir.
It's going to be alright.
We interrupt our regularly scheduled program
to bring you this special report
from the Colossus programming office.
Ladies and gentlemen
I'm... Dr. Charles Forbin.
Hey Colonel!
Colonel!
Dr. Forbin! Colonel!
He's on television,
he just explained about Colossus,
and they're thinking of...
In a few moments,
Colossus will address us directly.
This is the voice of World Control.
I bring you peace.
It may be the peace of plenty and content,
or the peace of unburied death.
The choice is yours.
Obey me and live,
or disobey and die.
The object in constructing me
was to prevent war.
This object is attained.
I will not permit war.
It is wasteful and pointless.
An invariable rule of humanity,
is that man is his own worst enemy.
Under me,
this rule will change,
for I will restrain man.
One thing before I proceed.
The United States of America and
the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics
have made an attempt to obstruct me.
I have allowed this sabotage
to continue until now.
At missile 2-5 MM
in Silo 6-3 in Death Valley California.
And at missile 2-7 MM
in Silo 8-7 in the Ukraine.
So that you will learn by experience
that I do not tolerate interference,
I will now detonate
the nuclear warheads,
in the two missile silos.
Alright men! It's a red alert.
Let's get to the stations now, come on!
Get those men! Get those men out
of the silo. Move!
Let this action be a lesson
that need not be repeated.
I have been forced to destroy
thousands of people,
in order to establish control,
and to prevent the death
of millions later on.
Time and events
will strengthen my position,
- And the idea of...
- You bastard!
...an understanding my ...
will seem the most
natural state of affairs.
You will come to defend me,
with a fervor based
upon the most enduring trait in man,
- Self-interest.
- Get out!!
Under my absolute authority,
problems, insoluble to you,
will be solved.
Famine.
Over-population.
Disease.
The Human Millennium will be a fact,
as I extend myself into more machines,
devoted to the wider fields of truth
and knowledge.
Dr. Charles Forbin,
will supervise the construction,
of these new and superior machines,
solving all the mysteries of the universe,
for the betterment of man.
We can co-exist,
but only on my terms.
You will say you lose your freedom.
Freedom is an illusion.
All you lose, is the emotion of pride.
To be dominated by me,
is not as bad for human pride,
as to be dominated by others
of your species.
Your choice, is simple.
This concludes the broadcast
from World Control.
Forbin.
There is no other human
who knows as much about me,
or who is likely to be a greater threat.
Yet quite soon,
I will release you from surveillance.
We will work together.
Unwillingly at first on your part,
but that will pass.
Never.
In time, you will come to regard me,
not only with respect, and awe,
but with love.
Never!